Guide to the Barbara Wertheim Tuchman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Barbara Wertheim Tuchman papers
1920-1982
MS 574
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20.5
(40 boxes, 6 folios)
The papers consist of correspondence, articles, speeches, printed material, research materials, photographs, and drafts of books relating to Barbara Tuchman's literary career, including such works as Bible and Sword, The Zimmermann Telegram, The Guns of August, and The Proud Tower.
Tuchman, Barbara W. (Barbara Wertheim), 1912-1989
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Barbara Tuchman 1965, 1979, and 1982, and Book of the Month Club, 1971.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Personal. II. Writings.
Biographical / Historical
Barbara Wertheim Tuchman was born in 1912, and received her B.A. degree from Radcliffe College in 1933. She served as a research assistant for the Institute for Pacific Relations, 1934-1935; was an editorial assistant at The Nation, 1936-1937; a staff writer for War in Spain, London, 1937-1938; American correspondent for New Statesman and Nation, London, 1939; and was with the Far East news desk, OWI, 1944-1945. Tuchman was best known as the author of many books and articles. She was the recipient of the Pulitzer Prize in 1963 and 1972. Tuchman died in 1989.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, articles, speeches, printed material, research materials, photographs, and drafts of books relating to Barbara Tuchman's literary career, including such works as Bible and Sword, The Zimmermann Telegram, The Guns of August, and The Proud Tower.
Authors -- Biography; Historians -- Biography; Women; World War, 1939-1945; Asia; Tuchman, Barbara W. (Barbara Wertheim), 1912-1989
- Personal, 1920, 1932-1933, 1935-1940, 1956, 1958-1959, 1962-1968; Series I; .5 linear feet (1 Box 2 Folios)
  Scope and Contents
  Personal materials contain correspondence, documents, printed material, reprints, lists, phonograph records, newspaper clippings and handwritten drafts, Included in this series are biographical information, letters of rejection from publishers, information about Mrs. Tuchman's service on various committees, honorary degrees, early writings from childhood and college, a scrapbook of clippings of her early journalistic work, a phonograph record of an interview with Mrs. Tuchman and miscellaneous lists and reprints.
  The series is arranged by type of material; and within each type is in chronological order.
  - Biographical information; autobiographical sketch and photo., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
  - Correspondence; rejections from agent and publishers., 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pulitzer Prize in biography; correspondence, list of submitted books, and recommendations., 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Society of American Historians; Parkman Prize, correspondence regarding position as judge., 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Society of American Historians; Parkman Prize Presentation, speech to Daniel Boorstein., 1966, March 31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Society of American Historians; (Parkman Prize), program and menu., 1966, March 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commission on Presidential Scholars; correspondence, printed material., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Committee for an Effective Congress; correspondence concerning contributions., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Yale University Committee on Humanities; correspondence and report., 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Columbia University - Honorary Degree; Doctor of Letters, honoris causa., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hebrew Union College - Honorary Degree; Doctor of Humane Letters., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - New School for Social Research - Honorary Degree, Doctor of Letters., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - University of Massachusetts - Honorary Degree, Doctor of Humane Letters, honoris causa., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Yale University - Honorary Degree, Doctor of Humane Letters; notification, citation., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - First essay in history; "The People Who Settled on the Coast of America," illustration by Dr. Van Loon., 1920 (ca.) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "The Duke of Buckingham and Foreign Affairs"; a paper for History II, Radcliffe., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "The Englishman Presents His Empire"; Honors Thesis at Radcliffe., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oversize scrapbook of early journalism (folio 1A)., 1935-1940 (Box 1A)
  - Notes on preface for book on cooking., undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - List of sponsors for dinner honoring Barbara Tuchman., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - List of people in Chicago., undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Newspaper clipping; obituary of Charles Morton, editor of Atlantic Monthly, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Phonograph record; P. Gravina interview with Barbara Tuchman (folio 1B) [restricted], 1956 (Box 1B)
    - Duplicating master (1BD) [restricted] (Box 1BD)
    - Use copy (1BU) (Box 1BU)
  - Stamps for Britannica research service. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - U.S. Copyright Law - highlights., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Writings, 1953-1969; Series II; 9.5 linear feet (24 Boxes, 4 Folios, 6 Card file boxes)
  The material contained in this series includes books, articles, a broadcast, letters to the editor, a poem, reviews, and speeches.
  The books include Bible & Sword, The Zimmermann Telegram, The Guns of August, and The Proud Tower. They are arranged alphabetically by title. Included within each unit are the correspondence, research materials, various drafts, and illustrations, pertinent to the various works.
  The articles and speeches are basically arranged chronologically, as are the letters to the editor. These writings cover such topics as historical events, current affairs and historiography. A fairly substantial section of the writings pertains to Israel.
  The reviews deal with Thomas Woodrow Wilson by William C. Bullitt and Sigmund Freud, Ludendorff by D.J. Goodspeed, Justice in Jerusalem by Gideon Hausner, The Fall of Paris by Alistair Horne, Dare Call It Treason by Richard M. Watt, and Hitler's Spies and Saboteurs by Charles Wighton and Gunter Peis. The reviews are arranged alphabetically by the name of the author of the book.
  - BOOKS
    - Bible and Sword
      - Correspondence, 1953-1957, 1967-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 32-37)
      - Correspondence; financial and business, 1957-1969 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Correspondence Research material, news clipping on Palestine (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Research material - article, "Strategic Cyprus", 1953 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Bibliography notes, general reference (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Bibliography notes chapter 4 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Bibliography notes chapter 5-8 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Bibliography notes chapter 9-13 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Bibliography notes chapter 14-17 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Handwritten research notes
        - Chapter 1, "Origins" (Box 2, Folder 46)
        - Chapter 2, "Joesph" (Box 2, Folder 47)
        - Chapter 3, "Pilgrims" (Box 2, Folder 48)
        - Chapter 4, "Crusades" (Box 2, Folder 49)
        - Chapter 5, "Bible" (Box 2, Folder 50)
        - Chapter 6, "Elizabethans" (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - Chapter 7, "Puritans" (Box 3, Folder 52)
        - Chapter 8, "18th Century" (Box 3, Folder 53)
        - Chapter 9, "Napoleon & Mehemet" (Box 3, Folder 54)
        - Chapter 10, "Shaftesbury" (Box 3, Folder 55)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 3, Folder 56)
        - Chapter 11, "Jewish Nationalism" (Box 3, Folder 57)
        - Chapter 13, "P.E.F." (Box 3, Folder 58)
        - Chapter 16 (Box 3, Folder 59)
        - Chapter 17, "Balfour, B.D. Mandate" (Box 3, Folder 50)
        - Empire (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - Mandate Period in Palestine, A-D (Box 3, Folder 52)
        - Mandate Period in Palestine, E-L (Box 3, Folder 63)
        - Mandate Period in Palestine, M-R (Box 3, Folder 64)
        - Mandate Period in Palestine, T-W, miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 65)
        - Mandate Period in Palestine, General (Box 3, Folder 66)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 67)
      - Typescripts
        - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 68)
        - Chapter 1 (Box 4, Folder 69)
        - Chapter 2 (carbon) (Box 4, Folder 70)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 4, Folder 71)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 4, Folder 72)
        - Epilogue (corrected) (Box 4, Folder 73)
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - Typescript of review by Alvin Johnson, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - Newspaper reviews, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Excerpts from reviews, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - The Zimmermann Telegram
      - Correspondence, 1955-1960, 1962, 1964-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 78-86)
      - Correspondence - Royalties and printing commitments, 1957-1969 (Box 5, Folder 87)
      - Research material - War Department: "Report on Cryptographic Background" - Friedman, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 88)
      - Research material - copy of decipherment of telegram, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 89)
      - Problems concerned with telegram (Box 5, Folder 90)
      - Research material; copy of articles from New Orleans paper, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 91)
      - Research material: newsclippings, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 92)
      - List of sources for material (Box 5, Folder 93)
      - Handwritten notes for book (Box 5, Folder 94)
      - Miscellaneous handwritten notes (Box 5, Folder 95)
      - Research note cards, Chapters 1, 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
      - Handwritten research notes (Box 5, Folder 97)
      - Research note cards
        - Chapters 3, 4, undated (Box 5, Folder 98)
        - Chapters 5, 6, undated (Box 6, Folder 99)
        - Chapters 7, 8, undated (Box 6, Folder 100)
        - Chapters 9, 10, undated (Box 6, Folder 101)
        - Chapters 11, 12, undated (Box 6, Folder 102)
        - Chapters 13, Bibliography, illustrations, undated (Box 6, Folder 103)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 104)
      - Bibliography file cards
        - Contemporary sources, undated (Box 6, Folder 105)
        - Secondary sources, undated (Box 6, Folder 106)
        - Preliminary lists of titles and chapters (Box 6, Folder 107)
        - Handwritten draft for chapter 10 (Box 6, Folder 108)
      - Final revisions
        - Chapter 1 (Box 6, Folder 109)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 6, Folder 110)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 6, Folder 111)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 6, Folder 112)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 6, Folder 113)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 6, Folder 114)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 6, Folder 115)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 7, Folder 116)
        - Chapter 9 (Box 7, Folder 117)
        - Chapter 10 (Box 7, Folder 118)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 7, Folder 119)
        - Chapter 12 (Box 7, Folder 120)
        - Chapter 13 (Box 7, Folder 121)
      - Carbons
        - Contents, Author's Note (Box 7, Folder 122)
        - Chapter 1, Prologue (Box 7, Folder 123)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 7, Folder 124)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 7, Folder 125)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 7, Folder 126)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 7, Folder 127)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 7, Folder 128)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 7, Folder 129)
        - Chapter 9 (Box 7, Folder 130)
        - Chapter 10 (Box 7, Folder 131)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 7, Folder 132)
        - Chapter 12 (Box 7, Folder 133)
        - Chapter 13 (Box 7, Folder 134)
        - Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 135)
        - Appendix (Box 7, Folder 136)
        - Notes for book (Box 7, Folder 137)
        - Corrections (Box 7, Folder 138)
      - Proofreader's copy
        - Contents, Author's Note, Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 139)
        - Prologue (Box 7, Folder 140)
        - Chapter 1 (Box 7, Folder 141)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 7, Folder 142)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 7, Folder 143)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 7, Folder 144)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 7, Folder 145)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 7, Folder 146)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 7, Folder 147)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 8, Folder 148)
        - Chapter 9 (Box 8, Folder 149)
        - Chapter 10 (Box 8, Folder 150)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 8, Folder 151)
        - Notes for book (Box 8, Folder 152)
      - New Edition, Preface and corrections, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 153)
      - Illustration - Zimmermann telegram key (folio 3), undated (Box 8A)
      - Illustrations; photos and reproductions of telegram, code, etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 155)
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 8, Folder 156-157)
      - Notes about book (Constable) (Box 8, Folder 158)
      - Summary of book, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 159)
      - Publicity folder (Constable), undated (Box 8, Folder 160)
      - Review (Box 8, Folder 161)
      - Review of work - "The Cryptogram", 1960 (Box 8, Folder 162)
      - Feature supplement of book in Reader's Digest, 1959, January (Box 8, Folder 163)
      - Assistance on Zimmermann facts for Webster's Biographical Dictionary, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 164)
      - Article written on Zimmermann for Collier's Encyclopedia - correspondence, contract, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 165)
      - Article written on Zimmermann for Encyclopedia Britannica - correspondence, carbon, citation, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 166)
      - "The Persian Gulf Prelude to the Zimmermann Telegram" - C.S. Edmonds, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 167)
    - Guns of August
      - Correspondence, 1958-1967, undated (Box 9, Folder 168-177)
      - Correspondence financial and business matters, 1961-1969 (Box 9, Folder 178-180)
      - Correspondence xerox copies of letters by Barbara Tuchman to Macmillan Company [Cecil Scott, et al] (Box 9, Folder 181)
      - Correspondence; with Denning Miller; criticism of book, 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 182)
      - Research material; pamphlet on Imperial War Museum (Box 10, Folder 183)
      - Research material; trips for book - postcard photos (Box 10, Folder 184)
      - Bibliography cards; Belgian, British, French (Box 10, Folder 185)
      - Bibliography cards; German, Russian, Turkish Secondary, Official (Box 10, Folder 186)
      - Bibliography cards; U.S., miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 187)
      - Book with bibliographic entries, undated (Box 10, Folder 188)
      - Handwritten notes on maps and illustrations, undated (Box 10, Folder 189)
      - Research material - trips for book, maps, booklets, notes (Box 10, Folder 190)
      - Research material; map of Northern Poland (Box 10, Folder 191)
      - Printed and handrawn maps (Box 10, Folder 192)
      - Handwritten research notes (Box 10, Folder 193)
      - Miscellaneous research materials (Box 10, Folder 194)
      - Research note cards, chapter 1-13 (card file box 10A) (Box 10A)
      - Research note cards, chapters 14-22, unused (card file box 10B) (Box 10B)
      - Successive outlines for book (Box 10, Folder 197)
      - Handwritten drafts
        - Prologue (Box 11, Folder 198)
        - Chapter 1 (Box 11, Folder 199)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 11, Folder 200)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 11, Folder 201)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 11, Folder 202)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 11, Folder 203)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 11, Folder 204)
        - Chapter 12 (Box 11, Folder 205)
        - Chapter 13 (Box 11, Folder 206)
        - Chapter 14 (Box 11, Folder 207)
        - Chapter 15 (Box 11, Folder 208)
        - Chapter 16 (Box 11, Folder 209)
        - Chapter 17 (Box 11, Folder 210)
        - Chapter 18 (Box 11, Folder 211)
        - Chapter 19 (Box 11, Folder 212)
        - Chapter 20 (Box 11, Folder 213)
        - Chapter 21 (Box 11, Folder 214)
        - Chapter 22 (Box 11, Folder 215)
        - Notes (Box 11, Folder 216)
      - Carbons
        - Author's Note, Chapter 1 (Box 12, Folder 217)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 12, Folder 218)
        - Chapters 3 and 4 (Box 12, Folder 219)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 12, Folder 220)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 12, Folder 221)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 12, Folder 222)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 12, Folder 223)
        - Chapter 9 (Box 12, Folder 224)
        - Chapter 10 (Box 12, Folder 225)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 12, Folder 226)
        - Chapter 12 (Box 12, Folder 227)
        - Chapter 13 (Box 12, Folder 228)
        - Chapter 14 (Box 12, Folder 229)
        - Chapter 15 (Box 12, Folder 230)
        - Chapter 16 (Box 12, Folder 231)
        - Chapter 17 (Box 12, Folder 232)
        - Chapter 18 (Box 12, Folder 233)
        - Chapter 19 (Box 12, Folder 234)
        - Chapter 20 (Box 12, Folder 235)
        - Chapter 21 (Box 12, Folder 236)
        - Chapter 22 (Box 12, Folder 237)
        - Afterword (Box 12, Folder 238)
        - Notes (Box 12, Folder 239)
        - Directions and comments to copy editor on typography, placing of maps (Box 13, Folder 240)
      - Proofreader's copy
        - Author's Note, Contents (Box 13, Folder 241)
        - Chapter 1 (Box 13, Folder 242)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 13, Folder 243)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 13, Folder 244)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 13, Folder 245)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 13, Folder 246)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 13, Folder 247)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 13, Folder 248)
        - Chapter 9 (Box 13, Folder 249)
        - Chapter 10 (Box 13, Folder 250)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 13, Folder 251)
        - Chapter 12 (Box 13, Folder 252)
        - Chapter 13 (Box 13, Folder 253)
        - Chapter 14 (Box 13, Folder 254)
        - Chapter 15 (Box 13, Folder 255)
        - Chapter 16 (Box 13, Folder 256)
        - Chapter 17 (Box 13, Folder 257)
        - Chapter 18 (Box 13, Folder 258)
        - Chapter 19 (Box 13, Folder 259)
        - Chapter 20 (Box 13, Folder 260)
        - Chapter 21 (Box 13, Folder 261)
        - Chapter 22 (Box 13, Folder 262)
        - Afterword, Bibliography (Box 14, Folder 263)
        - Illustrations (Box 14, Folder 264)
        - Notes (Box 14, Folder 265)
        - Index (Box 14, Folder 266)
      - Miscellaneous fragments of typescript (Box 14, Folder 267)
      - Criticism of original drafts by Denning Miller, 1960-1961 (Box 14, Folder 268)
      - Illustrations, 10 maps (folio 14A) (Box 14A)
      - Illustrations, set of negatives (folio l4A) (Box 14A)
      - Illustrations, 2 photos (folio 14A) (Box 14A)
      - Illustrations; photos from Imperial War Museum (Box 14, Folder 272)
      - Newspaper clippings on book, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 273)
      - Excerpts from reviews of book (Box 14, Folder 274)
      - Foreign reviews, 1962-1963 (Box 14, Folder 275)
      - German reviews, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 276)
      - Barbara Tuchman's comments on film version, undated (Box 14, Folder 277)
      - Reviews of film version, 1964-1965 (Box 14, Folder 278)
      - Photo and article with letter quoted by Barbara Tuchman - Joffe Weeping Ash, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 279)
      - Xerox copy of a page from "Baltzell's book," showing parallels to Tuchman's book, undated (Box 14, Folder 279A)
    - The Proud Tower
      - Correspondence, 1961-1967, undated (Box 15, Folder 280-287)
      - Correspondence - Royalties and printing commitments, 1963-1969 (Box 15, Folder 288)
      - Preliminary plans for book and principle characters, undated (Box 15, Folder 289)
      - Research material
        - With notes; pamphlet on Philharmonic Hall with article on "Electra" (p. B-G), 1964-1965 (Box 15, Folder 290)
        - And notes; translations of "Electra" and "Salome", 1943 (Box 15, Folder 291)
        - And notes; pamphlet on the Royal Palace "Het Huisten Bosch", undated (Box 15, Folder 292)
        - And notes; "The Genius of Richard Strauss" by Erich Leinsdorf, undated (Box 15, Folder 293)
        - Review of three books - Times Literary Supplement, 1961 November 10 (Box 15, Folder 294)
        - Concerning La Vida De Canalejas, Jose Francos Rodriguez (Box 15, Folder 295)
        - Typed excerpt from Memoirs of a Social-Democrat, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 296)
        - Reprint - "Im Reichstagsprasidum", 1928 (Box 15, Folder 297)
        - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 15, Folder 298)
      - Research material and notes; references and call slips, undated (Box 15, Folder 299)
      - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 300)
      - Research note cards
        - Chapters 1, 2, 3 (card file, box 15A) (Box 15A)
        - Chapters 4, 5 (card file, box 15B) (Box 15B)
        - Chapters 6, 7, 8 (card file, box 15C) (Box 15c)
        - Unused and bibliography (card file, box 15D) (Box 15D)
      - "The Anarchists"; Atlantic Monthly, published version of chapter from book, 1963, May (Box 15, Folder 305)
      - Notes and handwritten drafts
        - Foreword (Box 16, Folder 306)
        - Chapter 1 (Box 16, Folder 307)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 16, Folder 308)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 16, Folder 309)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 16, Folder 310)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 16, Folder 311)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 16, Folder 312)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 16, Folder 313)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 16, Folder 314)
      - First drafts; notes, references (Box 16, Folder 315)
      - First typescripts
        - Foreword, Chapter 1 (Box 16, Folder 316)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 16, Folder 317)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 17, Folder 318)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 17, Folder 319)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 17, Folder 320)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 17, Folder 321)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 17, Folder 322)
      - Carbons of final draft
        - Contents, Chapter 1 (Box 17, Folder 323)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 17, Folder 324)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 17, Folder 325)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 17, Folder 326)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 17, Folder 327)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 17, Folder 328)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 18, Folder 329)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 18, Folder 330)
        - Index (Box 18, Folder 331)
      - Style sheets and instructions for proofreader, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 332)
      - Typescript of proofreader
        - Captions, credits (Box 18, Folder 333)
        - Foreword (Box 18, Folder 334)
        - Chapter 1 (Box 18, Folder 335)
        - Chapter 2 (Box 18, Folder 336)
        - Chapter 3 (Box 18, Folder 337)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 18, Folder 338)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 18, Folder 339)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 19, Folder 340)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 19, Folder 341)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 19, Folder 342)
        - References, Bibliography, and Notes (Box 19, Folder 343)
        - Index (Box 19, Folder 344)
      - Galley proofs (folio 19A) (Box 19A)
      - Illustrations
        - Originals used for book, undated (Box 19, Folder 346)
        - Originals used for book (five drawings, cartoons), (folio 8A), undated (Box 19, Folder 347)
        - Wood block for one picture, undated (Box 20, Folder 348)
        - Not used - photos, drawings, cartoons, undated (Box 20, Folder 349)
        - Not used - negatives (Box 20, Folder 350)
        - Not used - French newspaper (folio 8A) (Box 20, Folder 351)
        - Not used (folio 8A), undated (Box 20, Folder 352)
      - Material for jacket copy, undated (Box 20, Folder 353)
      - Comments and critical remarks of galley proof (Box 20, Folder 354)
      - Weaknesses in book found by "Arnold B." (Box 20, Folder 355)
      - Selected excerpts from reviews, undated (Box 20, Folder 356)
      - Cover, Saturday Review, 1966 January 15 (Box 20, Folder 356A)
      - French reviews; newspaper clippings, duplicate copies, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 357)
      - Selection for This Is My Best; correspondence, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 358)
  - ARTICLES
    - Partial List of Articles by Barbara W. Tuchman (Box 21, Folder 359)
    - "Schedule Worship," Good Housekeeping, correspondence, 1957 (Box 21, Folder 360)
    - "Perdicaris Alive or Raisuli Dead," American Heritage [1959], 1958-1961, 1968
      - Correspondence (Box 21, Folder 361)
      - Research Notes (Box 21, Folder 362-363)
      - Sources, Note on illustrations (Box 21, Folder 364)
      - Outline of article and letter segment, undated (Box 21, Folder 365)
      - First version, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 366)